CHAPTER 6

Security Insights from the Buddhist
Principles in the 1910 BS
(1854 AD) Muluki Ain*

SHIVA PRASAD PAUDEL

HINDU SCRIPTURES WERE THE FUNDAMENTAL
SOURCE OF STATE LAW

In ancient Nepal, when it was ruled by Kirats, the Mundhum, a religious text of Kiratis, was believed to have ruled the country. (Wasti(1) 5). However, there was not adequate evidence of whether Mundhum was a normative standard or in practice. Some historians argue that Mundhum was the basis of day to day ruling of the society. Mundhum has a chapter of Kharom Thim, which deals with the system of justice (Wasti(1) 20).

In the time of Lichhavis, there was no reference to one law or code. The existing historical evidence are inscriptions alone. Most of them underline the establishment of Guthi (endowments of land) for the operation of Vihars and the performance of religious rites. These Guthis were kept for conducting pujas of Hindu and Buddhist Temples and for maintenance and operation of Hindu and Buddhist Temples and Buddhist Sangha and Vihars (monasteries).1

* This paper was presented at a seminar of academics and students at Lumbini Buddhist University on 10-11 March 2024 at Lumbini, Nepal.

In medieval Nepal, Jayasthiti Malla enacted a code, called Manav Nyayashastra. This Nayashastra is based on the Hindu belief system. (Wasti 21). It has referred to Hindu rituals, such as yagya (fire rituals), dana (donation) and the Hindu Varna system. It has quoted Narad Rishi and claimed that the code consists of dharmas propounded by Dharmadev. (Manav Nyayashastra, Wasti(2) 270). However, the account of the transaction, etc. also reflects that some of its provisions on property management and marriage were the insertion of the local customs and practices rather than the direct instructions of Hindu scriptures (dharmasastras). Balaram Kayastha has noted that Jayasthiti Malla cannot be entirely accused of destroying Buddhism in the valley. He was a devout Hindu practitioner but respectful of other religions. The restoration of Swyambhunath Chaitya after the attack of Shamsuddin was carried out in his time (Kayastha 141).

The rulers of Gorkha were also Hindus and they also adhere to the Varna system. The Thitis (a kind of royal decree) issued by Ram Shah mentions the enforcement of the Varna system (Muluki Ain 1910 BS: Annex 1). The appointment of Brahmins as Rajgurus, provision of danas (gifts) to Brahmins; and prohibition of capital punishment to Brahmins were specifically reflected in his Thitis. Prithvi Narayan Shah spent most of his life conquering other kingdoms, his ideas and values are reflected in his divine advice (Divya Upadesha). His Divya Upadesha reflects that he was an ardent Hindu devotee and he also instructed to keep a pundit/priest in every court to dispense justice as per the Nyayashastra/scripture). His advice clearly instructs the rulers and citizens to follow the traditions and religion (Kula Dharma) of their forefathers (Divya Upadesha, Wasti1 76, 81).

Rana Bahadur Shah’s sawal of 1863 BS reinforces the caste system, forbids the killing of cows (except Chauri, i.e. mount Ain cow/ Yak/Nak) and marriage against the established social practice (nachalyakorit). The sawal (a royal decree) of 1863 prohibited to destruction of the rest house of travellers (pati-pauwa), the religious site (dewal ) and the footbridge (sanghu) (Rana Bahadur Shah ko Bandobasta, Wasti1 76). Another piece of legislation before the Ain of 1910 BS was the Bandej (a typical form of administrative law) of Ujir Singh Thapa (Governor of Palpa Gauda/area), dated 1879 BS. In this Bandej, he had specifically mentioned that if someone unintentionally does an unlawful sexual act, which takes away his or her caste, s/he should be pardoned as per the scriptures (dharmashastra). (Fourth Bandej, nos. 17 and 20, Wasti(1) 105). This means that he is referring to the Hindu dharmashastra which provisions for the Varna system. However, his bandej also clearly mentions that adhering to the customs is not punishable, such as a marriage between cousins through maternal uncle and paternal aunt.2 (Fourth Bandej no. 19, Wasti(1)).

It is clear from the royal decree issued by Ram Shah, a royal order of Prithvi Narayan Shah and the administrative order issued by Ujir Singh Thapa that customary law was made part of the Nepalese legal order. However, a detailed study is yet to be carried out to what extent the provisions of Hindu scriptures were modified and customary laws got a greater space into the Nepalese legal system. Making an exception of killing cauri (Yak) from the offense of killing cows is a good example of such modification.

THE (MULUKI ) AIN OF 1910 BS: THE FIRST
COMPREHENSIVE CODE BASED ON HINDU
SCRIPTURES AND CUSTOMARY PRACTICES

The (Muluki) Ain or the National Code, 1854,3 (hereinafter the Ain) ruled the country until it was replaced by the new Muluki Ain of 2020 BS (1963 AD).4 The Prime Minister Jung Bahadur Kunwar Rana was the main initiator behind this codification (Wasti

25) (Khatiwoda 3). Wasti has named Lokpati Jha and Leshpati Jha as drafters of the Ain (Wasti 25). The Ain was discussed in the council of 219 office-bearers and was issued with their names printed in the preamble. The e-copy published by the Nepal Law Commission has included three royal orders issued by Shree Panch Prithvi Bir Bikram Shah Dev. The second royal order of 1943 BS records a major revision of the Ain in the same year. This rewriting was not only made to remove the repetitions but also to include well-established practices and customs into law.5 This order also allows the prime minister and the council to make changes in the law as per the customs and practices. Earlier to this date, two royal orders of 1910 BS and 1942 BS did not have any content to allow the prime minister and the council to accommodate the customs and practice into the law.

The Ain had regulated civil matters such as property, cash transactions, wages, adoption and marriage; criminal matters- such as gambling, witchcraft, rape, sexual intercourse, incest, murder and maintenance of caste-based-order; and Dharmadhikar, court procedure and evidential matters.

The preamble emphasizes the equal application of the law among people of the same caste, while formally accepting different treatment of individuals belonging to different castes as a legal principle. Thus, the Nepalese polity until 1963 was accused of ruling based on the Hindu belief system,6 which reinforces caste-based social order, non-killing of Brahmins, cows and women, etc. Despite the claim, the Ain fails to prescribe the comprehensive list of four Varnas and the six castes and their subgroups. Khatiwoda et al. have counted that the Ain has referred to sixty-three castes besides the castes within the Newar community (around twenty-six castes within Newar alone) and approximately seven ascetic groups (Khatiwoda 29). There could be two reasons for this anomaly. The first one is that the Varna system was developed in the southern plains long ago and they were ignorant of the diversity between people that existed in the northern Himalayan range and other far-off places. The second reason could be that over time practices of drinking alcohol and eating meat developed even within some communities, including Khasa, which traditionally fall either in Brahmin or Chhetri communities (Khatiwoda 30).

Interestingly, the four classifications of people among Hindu Scriptures—Brahmin, Kshetriya or Chhetris, Vaishya and Sudra, are not found in the Ain. The primary classification made by the Ain is—tagadhari (sacred thread-wearers), matawali (alcohol-drinkers but touchable and perhaps water-acceptable), and (fully) untouchable caste. Muslims and Christians were put under touchable but not water-acceptable castes. The Ain has used the term ‘European’ at a place and ‘mleccha’ at a couple of other places, which seems to mean Christians only.7 Except for one provision, which shall be discussed in another section, other provisions where Muslims, Christians and Europeans are mentioned for offenses, such as illicit sexual intercourse; protection from violence such as beating, being sold by the husband and goods that can be touched by Muslims and Christians.

The Ain is not entirely the reinforcement of Hindu practices. It has also given some space, though it looks contradictory to the modern belief system and customary practices. For example, the Ain has given the freedom to people to choose their livelihood as a cobbler, tailors and other forms of labour work.8 From Hindu Dharmashastra’s point of view, such acts should be prohibited for upper castes such as Brahmins and Chhetris.

SPECIFIC PROVISIONS ON THE DHARMIC PRACTICES
OF NON-HINDU TRADITIONS AND ASCETICS
WITHIN HINDU TRADITION

The Ain has a few provisions that can be interpreted to allow the customary practices of non-Hindu religions. However, the Ain are careful in preventing Hindu ascetics or non-householders from expanding their constituency.

In the chapter of Dharmadhikar, it is very affirmatively stated that all four castes including Muslims and Europeans can ‘perform any act that is in accordance with their family traditions and beliefs and leads to Dharma’ except slaughtering the cow.9 The Ain criminalizes an act of disturbance on the performance of such a dharmic act. This provision is very broad to provide everyone including Christians and Muslims to carry out tasks according to their family tradition.

There is only one direct Buddhist reference in the Ain, which does not read encouraging. Section 35 of the chapter on Dharmadhikar reads as follows:

When hearing the mantra (i.e., during the initiation), the members of Sacred Thread-wearing castes, including Brahmins and those belonging to Alcohol-drinking castes for whom it is customary to receive the initiation, shall hear and recite the mantra given by their guru according to their own tradition as followed by their fathers and forefathers (purkha). If they do not recite the mantra according to their own tradition as followed by their fathers and forefathers and follow the Buddhist path or any [other] atheistic jhanna-panna doctrine 411, a fine of 50 rupees shall be imposed on them. If they have themselves consumed cooked rice from a follower of the jhanna-panna doctrine and if they have also contaminated others [by feeding them cooked rice], their share of property shall, in accordance with the Ain, be confiscated. Their sacred thread shall be removed and they shall be degraded from their caste status.10

The above section can be divided into three parts. The first part promotes the continuation of the practice of receiving initiation and hearing and reciting mantras, which was carried out by their fathers and forefathers as a tradition. The emphasis was on the continuation of the same tradition without any alteration. Hence, the importance is given to the exact mantras given by the guru or the master. This practice is not only limited to the sacred thread-wearer but also to all the members where such tradition existed. The second part is applicable in a condition where a Hindu refuses to recite the mantra and converts to Buddhism or any other atheistic religion. In such case, one shall be imposed a fine. In the third part, one must lose property and caste, if one becomes a follower of the jhanna-panna doctrine together with eating the rice cooked by other followers and feeding the same to others.

Another provision of the Ain also prohibits a sacred-thread-wearer householder from hearing mantras11 primarily from the non-householder person or Fakir, which includes Sannyasi, Vairagi, Nanaka, Kanaphatta, Jogi, Jangam or Sebada. If a householder hears the mantra from these Fakirs or accepts them as their guru, he shall be fined (The chapter on Dharmadhikar, section 36). Likewise, these eight and other robe-wearers are prohibited to convert anyone with force or lure. Only persons above sixteen (including widows) were allowed to be converted into these practices if they wished. [The chapter on conversion to ascetics (Fakirsita Mudinya)]. The Ain notes that there were three kinds of Fakirs—one is the wanderer without anything, the second has the religious institution and the third one has the house and property. The Ain has prescribed separate punishment for these three types of Fakirs for making conversion [The chapter on conversion to ascetics (Fakirsita Mudinya), section 1]. In the context of death-related purification (Aasouch Barne), the Ain accepts the presence of Brahmacarin (celibate) in the then society but does not deal with it any further.

There are several references to above mentioned eight groups of Sannyasi, etc. and many other robe-wearers in the Ain but none of these provisions indicate that these renouncers were from the Buddhist faith. Such unclear provisions can be interpreted both in favour or against the Buddhist practitioner.

In the wake of having no provision in the Ain prohibiting customary religious practice, it can be stated that the Buddhist population or any other population can continue with their customary practices. However, if the Buddhist practice requires to carry out conversion of laity or people from other religions to the Buddhist path, this seems to have been prohibited by the Ain. The scheme of prohibition to conversion is not only applied to Buddhists but also to the other ascetic paths that traditionally fall under Hindus as well.

However, it is reasonable to accept that the Ain does not deal with the Buddhist Bajracaryas and the rest of the Buddhist Newars (Khatiwada, 33). It is also reasonable to state that the Ain neither wished to highlight the Buddhist practices of Kathmandu valley and elsewhere by putting a separate chapter nor risked forbidding these century-long practices.

The administrative power of the Buddhist Sangha has not been recognized by the State since the time of Manav Nyayashastra. It cannot be said that the administrative power of Sangha mentioned in the inscription of Pashupatinath-Vajraghar was an exception or a mainstream practice.

ESTABLISHMENT OF GUTHI AND CHARITABLE
ENDOWMENTS: A UNIQUE AND ESSENTIAL FEATURE
OF NEPALESE RELIGIOUS PRACTICE

The establishment and maintenance of Guthi have been an important feature of the promotion of religious and cultural practices in Nepal. It is well known that the Lichhavis had kept several Guthis for the pujas of temples and maintenance of Sangha and Vihars.12 Mostly in the times of Mallas, the inscription suggests the maintenance and restoration of the Buddhist and Hindu Temples and donation to public works, such as making wells and rest-house for travellers (pati-pauwas).13

The Ain has promoted the establishment of Guthi on Nepali soil and forbids establishment of Guthi in Indian religious places, namely, Kashi and Kedar. It provides two factual accounts of the confiscation of a Royal Guthi established by Rana Bahadur Shah and the denial of protection of the right to land and Shivalaya and a Dharmashala built in it by a former prime minister by the British India Government (The chapter on Datta Guthi, section 1). The Ain presents that Nepal has significant religious sites compared to India. It acclaims the high religious purity of Nepal by describing it as the only Hindu Kingdom in the Kali era. It praises the piousness of the country having Jyotirmaya Shree Pashupatinath and Shree Guheshwori and proclaims Nepal as a sacred place (punya bhumi). It clearly states the protection of Royal Guthi established from the time of Dravya Shah but does not refer to the protection of Guthi established before the Shah period. (The chapter on Datta Guthi, section 5). The Ain fails to recognize the historic contribution made by the Kings of Kathmandu Valley and other parts of Nepal in ancient and medieval times. Likewise, the Ain also does not admire the religious sanctity of Buddhist chaityas or shrines. Khatiwoda et al. have argued that ‘(t)he legal recognition of Guthi land can even be read as the integration of different (divine) forms of spatiality embedded in the state space’ (Khatiwoda 27), however, there is no specific reference to Buddhist stupas, chaityas that existed in the Himalayan, Hill and Terai region. Even if you believe that the rulers had a deep respect for Buddhist deities, that is not reflected in the black letter of the Ain.

Nonetheless, several provisions in the Ain protect the Guthi that were established from the time of fathers, forefathers and ancestors (The chapter on Datta Guthi, sections. 6-27).

The Ain promotes Guthi both for temples and other public works, etc., and charitable endowment (sadabarta) for paupers and Fakirs, etc. (the chapter on Datta Guthi, section 2). Khatiwoda et al. summarize the provisions in the Ain that highlight mainly three primary purposes for establishing Guthi and charitable endowment: religious and ritual purposes, such as the maintenance of Shiva temples, pilgrim’s refuges (Dharamsala) and the performance of compulsory, occasional or annul worship of deities (nitya- and naimittika-puja) (the chapter on Datta Guthi, section 1); welfare purposes, such as the daily distribution of meals to orphans, elderly people without family or disabled persons [the chapter on Poor (pauper), section 6] or the arrangement of funeral ceremonies (the chapter on Funerals, section 5); and, finally, the maintenance of public facilities, such as wayside shelters, fountains, bridges, ghatas, wells, ponds, paths, resting places or gardens (the chapter on Making Houses, section 9) (Khatiwoda 51).

The Ain documents the Nepalese tradition of establishing Guthi being carried out by Kings and Citizens from ancient times. However, there seems to be a difference in the trend. In the time of Lichhavis and Mallas, the Guthis were established for the performance of puja, maintenance of the temple and Buddhist Sangha. However, the Ain promotes charitable endowments for paupers and mendicants.

The Act has not failed to prescribe the protective measures to upkeep the Guthi as well as the punishment for harming Guthi. It prescribes that if kings and ministers confiscate Guthi or don’t give a replacement of Guthi land when confiscated, they will accumulate demerits (paap) and open the door to hell (The chapter on Datta Guthi, sections 1 and 25). The Ain established a separate administrative body (the Guthi Janch Adda) and a special court (the Guthi Kancahari) for the upkeeping of endowments (The chapter on Poor, section 6). Such offices were not known to have been established in the ancient or medieval period.

SOME OTHER CONSIDERATIONS TO INTERPRET
THE MULUKI AIN OF 1910 BS

The following two considerations are important to get a balanced picture of the reality before and during the time of Ain.

THE CONTRIBUTION OF SHAH KINGS TO THE
PRESERVATION OF BUDDHIST PRACTICES

There can be no doubt that the Shah Kings were Hindus. However, the words of Prithvi Narayan Shah, who is the founder of modern Nepal, did not have a policy of suppressing the customs and practices that were in operation from the time of their fathers and forefathers. It is said that he ordered the continuation of the Samyak Mahadan, which was discontinued after his victory over Kathmandu Valley and imposed a fine on those who refused to participate. He also did not stop any Buddhist religious festivals in Kathmandu Valley. Rana Bahadur Shah was known to have performed the puja of Mahamaya Bhairavi in accordance with a Boudha tantra. He also donated land to a Tibbetan Lama to establish a Guthi in 1786 AD. He also permitted the Tibetan Lama to establish the Dev Dharma Monastery and a temple of Mother Harati (Ghimire 144).

Surendra Bikram Shah is also known to have constructed a chaitya and put idols of Vajrapani and Dipankar in the Chaitya in Yatkha Bahal, Kathmandu. After the establishment of democracy in 2007 BS, King Tribhuvan visited Anandakuti Vihar on Buddha Jayanti. He was the kind who declared a national holiday on the day of Buddha Purnima.

Swaym bhunath Mahachaitya went under several renovations over a couple of centuries. For sure, a couple went under the Rana rule. Ranas did not oppose a major renovation which took place in the time of Rajendra Bir Bikram Shah (Shakya 2004).

RANA REGIME’S PROSECUTION OF THERAVADA MONKS

Xuanzang or Hiuen Tsang, in his travel account of the second half of the seventh century, also mentions his visit to two places in the present Nepal the country of Kapilvastu and the country of Nepal.14 (Li Rongxi 145, 171). Visiting Kapilvastu he mentions the condition of two palace cities which were completely deserted. In relation to the Buddhist practice, he writes ‘(t)here are more than one thousand ruined foundations of old monasteries and beside the palace city is a monastery inhabited by over three thousand monks, who study the Hinayana teachings of the Sammitiya school. There are two deva temples, with heretics (Hindu) living together’ (Li Rongxi 152). Regarding his impression of Kathmandu valley, he mentions ‘(t)he monasteries and deva temples are so close together that they touch each other and there are more than two thousand monks, who study both Mahayana and Hinayana teachings’ (Li Rongxi 192). It is also believed that out of nine missionary groups commissioned by King Asoka to propagate Buddhism in different places, one group of four monks led by Ven. Majjima came to Nepal and succeeded in propagating Buddhism in Nepal. It is popularly believed that Theravada Buddhism in practiced during Asoka’s time, which was also spread to Nepal. Unfortunately, for some unknown reason, the popularity of Buddhism declined and Vajrayana became the main Buddhist practice in Kathmandu Valley.15

An attempt at its resurgence took place in the early twentieth century but without success. In 1924 CE (1990 BS), Nanikaji Shrestha (known as Mahapragya), with other four monks—Mahachandra, Mahagyan, Mahavriya and Mahaksanti, wearing Buddhist robes, went on to the street of Kathmandu for alm collection. It was an unusual scene in the Kathmandu Valley. Prime Minister Chandrashamser exiled these five Buddhists for the crime of converting themselves to Buddhism (Ghimire 139). Mahapragya Nanikaji Shrestha together with another Bhikshu Amritananda (Lalkaji Shakya) came to Bhojpur from the Indian side to preach Buddhism in 1927 CE. The chief administrator (Badahakim) of the region arrested Mahapragya after learning that he was formally exiled by the government. They were exiled again to India upon receiving the order of Prime Minister Juddha Shamser (Ghimire 140).

However, these exiled Bhikshus did not give up. They organized themselves under the leadership of Bhikshu Amritananda. They mobilized international Buddhist communities to persuade the Nepalese government for allowing Buddhist practices. Bhikshu Amritananda was finally successful in establishing the first Theravada Bouddha Vihar in Swyambhunath in 1948 CE with the permission of the time of Prime Minister Mohan Shamser. Prime Minister Mohan Shamsher also permitted to give an official holiday to Buddhist followers on the day of Buddha Purnima (Ghimire 142).

CONCLUSION

The Ain uses the term ‘Buddhist’ only in one place. The use of the term also does not favour the promotion of Buddhist faith. However, it would be unsuitable to conclude that Buddhist practices were forbidden by the State. The account of Hiuen Tsang records the decline of Buddhism in the Kapilvastu area. Balaram Kayastha has also noted that Jayasthiti Malla cannot be entirely accused of destroying Buddhism in the valley.

It is well-established that the Buddhist religious practices started from the Lichhavi period. Hence, this was already established as the customary practice before the promulgation of the Ain. Hence, most (if not all) of the Buddhist practices should be well-protected under the recognition of customary religious practices under the Ain. Buddhist scriptures do not support killing in general and therefore the prohibition of cows cannot be interpreted as an interference with their religious practice. In terms of the public preaching of Buddhism, which has been an established practice since the time of Gautam Buddha seems not to be favoured by the Ain. The exile of Theravadin monks by the Rana regime in 1924 and 1927 AD, indicating the ban on Buddhist propagation can be interpreted as the suppression of Buddhist practices. The permission for the establishment of Anandakuti Vihar in 1948 can be taken as the beginning of the Theravadin practice in Nepal. Regarding, Himalayan or Mahayana Buddhism, their practice was not known to be interrupted by the Rana regime. They had legal protection under the rule of customary practice and their activities were also mostly unnoticed by the central administration.

Adopting the policy of promotion of the Guthi system by the Ain can be interpreted as non-interference to the established religious practice of Buddhism. This benefitted in continuing the practices of Buddhism. The donation or offering, though limited, made by the Kings and Ranas directly for the pujas, maintenance and renovation of Buddhist Chaityas and approval of offerings by other donors to maintain and renovate the Chaityas during the time of the Ain, does underline that the public policy was not against the Buddhist practice.

Though the Ain failed to include Nepal’s Buddhist glory in its text, neither Ranas nor Shahs were known to have suppressed any customary Buddhist practices. They might have made very little financial contribution but they were known to discourage the contributors as well. Nonetheless, we could sense from the reading of Muluki Ain that Buddhist communities must have had a tremendous struggle to avoid the cloud of fear hanging above them.

NOTES

1. Infra note 13.

2. This rule has continued to the Muluki Ain of 1910 BS (see, the chapter on Marriage, section 18). Likewise, the recognition of customary practices of Killing a wife’s adulterer also continued in the Ain of 1910 BS (see, the chapter on Adultery to a Woman from Enslaveable Caste, section 12 and most of the provisions in the chapter on Miscellaneous Regulations Concerning Adultery).

3. The author reviewed the Muluki Ain, 1910 BS published by the Nepal Law Commission on its website as of 30 January 2024. This version of the Muluki Ain is not the original copy but with several amendments. (Wasti 25). Annex-Chha (7) of the document states that it was issued in the reign of Shree Panch Prithvi Bir Bikram Shah Dev and Prime Minister Shree Teen Chandra Shamser in 1958 BS. The annexes Cha and Chha (6 and 7) state that the first amendment was made in 1943 BS in the reign of Shree Panch Prithvi Bir Bikram Shah Dev and Prime Minister Shree Teen Bir Shamser. However, Wasti has claimed that the Ain was amended several times. It is pertinent to mention that when originally enacted, it did not receive the name Muluki. The addition of Muluki before the word ‘Ain’ was the later development (Wasti 25).

4. The preamble of the Ain also mentions the names of three generations of Kings chiefly Shree Panch Rajendra Bir Bikram Shah Dev and Trailokya Bir Bikram Shah Dev. The scheme was to endorse the Ain by the former King and the crown prince (Wasti 25) and (Khatiwoda 3).

5. It is not definite which was the Hindu belief system or which was the actual practice developed in Nepal. However, some authors have argued that the Muluki Ain of 1854 codified customary law (Khatiwoda 2). A detailed analysis is yet to happen to what extent the scriptures were applied and to what extent they were modified.

6. A researcher has given a few examples of how the Manusmrti made its way to the Ain. (Khatiwoda1 6-18).

7. For the use of the term European, see the chapter on Dharmadhikar. For the use of the term Christian, see the chapter on Drinking Liquor and Untouchability. For the use of the term Mleccha, see the chapter on Dharmadhikar, section 38; the chapter on Miscellaneous Regulations Concerning Adultery, section 2; the chapter on Illicit Sexual Intercourse with Water-unacceptable Castes, section 1; and the chapter on Untouchable Class, section 17. For the use of the term Muslims, see the chapter on Beating between Father and Son, section 19; the chapter on Selling the Wife, secs. 1 and 2; the chapter on Drinking Liquor and Untouchability, section 2; the chapter on Dharmadhikar, section 38; the chapter on Miscellaneous Regulations Concerning Adultery, section 2; the chapter on Illicit Sexual Intercourse with Water-unacceptable Castes, sections 1 and 6; the chapter on Miscellaneous Regulations Concerning Adultery, sec. 2; the chapter on Illicit Sexual Intercourse with Water-unacceptable Castes, sections 1, 4, 5, 6 and the bottom table of the chapter on Untouchable Castes. Muslims and Christians have been designated as water-unacceptable but touchable castes. (Khatiwoda 32).

8. The chapter on Choosing a Profession, section 7.

9. The translation was by Khatiwoda et al. (Khatiwoda 490). See the chapter of Dharmadhikar, section 1.

10. Ibid., 502.

11. Khatiwoda et al. have stated that this provision applies while hearing the mantra during initiation. However, the plain text of the Ain does not indicate so. The mantra reciting practices are the established practice in Hinduism and can take place on other occasions as well.

12. Inscription in Lichhavi period compiled by (Bajracharya1): Guthi(s) in Swyambhu (pp. 384-5), Dhokatol (p. 386), Lalitpur-Chapa Tole and Kantipur-Musumbahal (p. 507), Sankhu (508), Patan-Mangalbazar-Bhimsen Mandir (p. 454), Pashupati-Vajraghar (pp. 499-506), Handigaun (p. 320).

13. Pre-medieval or later Lichhavi period inscription by (Bajracharya 2): Sankhu Vajrayogini (p. 37), Lalitpur-Kumbheswor (p. 229), Lalitpur Pimbahal (pp. 150-1), Swyambhu (p. 157), etc.

14. (Li Rongxi 145, 171). The Great Tang Dynasty Record of the Western Regions, Bukkyo Dendo Kyokai and Numata Center for Buddhist Translation and Research, Berkeley.

15. https://web.archive.org/web/20140804160554/http://www.lumbini.org.uk/bd_n_thera_t.html.

REFERENCES

Bajracharya, Dhanavajra (1), Licchavikalin Abhilekh (Inscription from the Lichhavi Period), Center for Nepal and Asian Studies, TU (2053 BS).

Bajracharya, Dhanavajra (2), Madhyakalin Licchavi Abhilekh (Inscription from the Medieval Lichhavi Period), Center for Nepal and Asian Studies, TU (2068 BS).

Ghimire, Chandrakala, Nepalma Buddha Dharmako Itihas (History of Buddhism in Nepal), Bhunipuran Prakashan (2079 BS).

Kayastha, Balaram, Prachin the Madhyakalin Nepalko Itihas (the Ancient and Medieval History of Nepal), Pallav Publication, Nepal (2077 BS).

Khatiwoda, Rajan, Cubelic, Simon, and Michael Axel, The Muluki Ain of 1854 (English Translation), Heidelberg University Publishing, (2023 CE).

Li Rongxi, The Great Tang Dynasty Record of the Western Regions, Bukkyo Dendo Kyokai and Numata Center for Buddhist Translation and Research, Berkeley (1996 AD).

Muluki Ain, 1910 BS (Nepali Copy), Nepal Law Commission.

Shakya, Min Bahadur, Sri Swayambhu Mahachaitya, Swayambhu Vikash Mandal, Swayambhu, Kathmandu (2004 AD).

Wasti, Prakash (1), Kanoon Sambandhi Kehi Aitihasik Abhilekhharu (Some Historical Documents Related to Law), Kanoon Sahaprakashan (2063 BS).

Wasti, Prakash (2), Hamro Kanooni Itihaskakehi-Jhankiharu (Some Pictures of our Legal History), Pairavi Book House (2063 BS).

CHAPTER 7

Third Country Resettlement a
‘Tryst with Destiny’ of Bhutanese
Asylum Seekers in Nepal

SARITA NANDMEHAR

INTRODUCTION

With a population of 8,21,329 (Bhutan Population, 2018), Bhutan has predominantly been a multi-ethnic society. Rich in natural resources including water, Bhutan is one of the countries where the parameter to index the country’s growth stands as Gross National Happiness (GNH) unlike Gross Domestic Product (GDP) followed around the world. Considered as one of the happiest and most peaceful places in the world, its past has a different narration of history. Major being the expulsion of the Lohtshampas in the 1990s. While the royal state machinery worked round the clock to ensure their expulsion, it became one of the biggest humanitarian tragedies of the time. Further, it took the shape of a serious ethnic conflict which was rooted in the majority that the Drukpa community’s fear had about the domination by the migrant Nepalese Lohtshampas whose population increased phenomenally over the years. To counter this demographic challenge, Drukpa restricted them to the disease-prone southern Bhutan, their movement inside Bhutan and they were not allowed to purchase land and property in other parts of Bhutan (Rose, 1977). As a result, Lohtshampas were isolated socially, culturally and economically isolated.

Bhutan’s Lohtshampas are the descendants of peasant farmers from Nepal who began to migrate to southern Bhutan after the Anglo-Bhutanese war of 1865. Successive generations cleared the forests and formed agrarian communities that quickly became Bhutan’s main producers of food. Their numbers were augmented by later migrants, who continued to be brought in by licensed contractors until about 1930. The Nepali settlers became the kingdom’s main source of cash income: unlike the Drukpas of the north, who paid their taxes in kind right up until the late 1950s, British colonial records show that Nepali settlers in southwest Bhutan were paying taxes in cash even before the Bhutanese monarchy was established in 1907. Until the 1950s, Bhutan was not a unified polity; different systems of administration were maintained in different parts of the country. In the south, the local contractors and their descendants remained powerful. The revenue raised in certain southern districts was submitted not to the central government but to a local governor based across the Indian border in Kalimpong (Hutt M., 2003, 2005).

In the 1950s, major administrative shuffling took place under the leadership of King Jigme Dorji Wangchuk and Prime Minister Jigme Palden Dorji. Several programmes concerning the development of the country and after due process, these programmes were institutionalized. As a result, a National Assembly was elected under the royal rule and the enforcement of Bhutan’s Nationality Law. While the state machinery was institutionalized and their functionaries were clearly defined to protect the ethnic diversity in the country, protecting the rights of minorities was emphasized upon. Also, it was under the 1958 Nationality Law that granted Lohtshampas full citizenship. Meanwhile, to understand the issue of the Lohtshampas, it is relevant to mention the Nationality Law.

The Nationality Law of Bhutan, published in 1958, was reiterated by the Bhutanese government after the 1990s (Hutt M., 2003). In 1958, during the 11th session, the National Assembly of Bhutan enacted the Nationality Act of Bhutan, 1958. It granted the Bhutanese nationality for the first time to all Nepalese who had settled in the Bhutanese Kingdom before 31 December 1958 and applied under naturalization (Hutt M., 2003). Under the following provisions:

1. A person would be considered a Bhutanese national by birth if his/her father was a Bhutanese national, regardless of the person’s birth.

2. A foreigner could become a Bhutanese citizen by presenting a petition to an official appointed by His Majesty the Druk Gyalpo and takes an oath of loyalty according to the rules laid down by the official. It again required:

(a) Resided in Bhutan for more than 10 years, i.e. age of majority.

(b) Owns agricultural land within the kingdom.

(c) Has served satisfactorily in government service for at least five years.

3. Foreign wife of a Bhutanese national also required a petition to the king and taking an oath of loyalty.

4. A person could also be deprived of citizenship by becoming citizenship of another country, leaving the country permanently and abandoning the agricultural land (MHA, GoB, 1958).

The government decided to bring the Bhutanese of Nepali origin into the mainstream Drupka culture. The king of Bhutan introduced an ideology of ‘One Nation, One People’ which led to the imposition of a code of conduct, including Drukpa language, religion and dress for all Bhutanese citizens through a policy of Driglam Namzha (a revival of traditional Bhutanese culture). The primary objective of this policy has been to establish national homogeneity and cohesion among the various linguistic and ethnic groups in the country. In addition to the Driglam Namzha Policy, the government adopted various policies and passed several resolutions in its National Assembly that went against the interest of the Bhutanese of Nepali origin (MHA, GoB, 1958).

In general, the nationality law of 1958 of Bhutan provided three ways to attain citizenship. Firstly, by birth to a father who is a Bhutanese national, secondly, a petition to an official to provide certain conditions of residences and government employment were met and a petition to an official upon marriage to a Bhutanese national. Also, a petition was required on the oath of the loyalty (Hutt M., 2003).

To restrict fresh entries of migrants to Bhutan, the King introduced a new Law in the year 1977. The Citizenship Act of 1985 created more hurdles regarding both the acquisition and termination of citizenship.

THE CENSUS, 1988

The census of 1988 was implemented on the basis of the 1985 citizenship Act. Firstly, the census was conducted by the Bhutanese government only in the five southern districts of Bhutan. Secondly, the authorities excluded ethnic Nepalese from becoming naturalized citizens, as approved for under the 1985 Act.

Instead, the authorities restricted Bhutanese citizenship of ethnic Nepalese who had records, such as tax receipts, to prove residence in Bhutan in 1958, i.e., 30 years before the census. Bhutanese officials refused to accept residency records from the years 1957 and 1959 indicating residency in 1958 to establish citizenship (Human Rights Watch, 2007). They disregarded the citizenship identity cards issued after the previous census: the authorities classified people who could not prove residence in 1958 as non-nationals, ‘returned migrants’, or other illegal immigrant categories, even if they possessed a citizenship card (Amnesty International, 1994). On the basis of it, people were divided into following categories:

TABLE 7.1: CATEGORY OF MIGRANT

Category | Type | Definition
F1 | Genuine Bhutanese Citizens | –
F2 | Returned Migrants | People who left Bhutan and then returned
F3 | Drop-out cases | People who were not around at the time of the census
F4 | Non-national women married to Bhutanese men and their children | –
F5 | Non-national men married to Bhutanese women and their children | –
F6 | Adoption cases | Children who are legally adopted and lastly
F7 | No nationals | Migrants and illegal settlers

Source: Amnesty International, 1992.

In 1989, the government undertook a survey and realized that the number of Nepali-speaking people was rapidly growing. It led them to adopt a policy called ‘Driglam Namzha’ or ‘One Nation and One People’. Generally, it seems reasonable for a country to adopt such kind of policy but it was not suitable to Bhutan due to the existence of different groups with different cultural practices, religions and languages the government wanted to impose the Nagalong culture, on every citizen.

In 1991, there was a protest against the policy and peaceful demonstration for supporting human rights. But the Voluntary Migration Form were printed in Dzongkha language, which most of the Nepali-speaking people were unable to read. As a result, many who filled it were indirectly giving up their citizenship of Bhutan. This led to the creation of many refugees in Bhutan. Apart from that, the Indian government denied asylum for the Bhutanese refugees and consequently, they had to leave for Nepal and are still remaining in camps since the 1990s.

Though the Royal Government of Bhutan has its own version of the exodus, accounts given by refugees, interviews with refugees’ leaders, reports by various human rights organizations and media reports lead us to the conclusion that the exodus of refugees from Bhutan has been broadly in four categories (Kharat, 2007):

• Bhutanese who had been forcefully evicted.

• Bhutanese who had voluntarily emigrated.

• Non-Bhutanese.

• Bhutanese who had committed criminal acts.

Out of these four categories, Thimphu agreed to the return of the people who belonged to the first category, although it felt that most of the refugees in United Nation High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) camps in eastern Nepal were originally Nepalese and Indian citizens looking for free food and shelter and health care. However, in subsequent bilateral talks, particularly during 1993-6, both Bhutan and Nepal took a more rigid stand regarding the repatriation of Bhutanese refugees (Kharat, 2007).

Till date, in the last 20 years, 15 bilateral talks and many other informal dialogues have taken place. But the government of Bhutan and Nepal could not reach a consensus and conclusion to find a permanent solution. The situation remains unchanged.

The UN convention on Refugees after the cold war in the 1960s and 1980s came into for that reason. However, the repatriation process was adopted in Nepal in 2007. In Article 1 of the statute of UNHCR there are three options for a durable solution:

• Repatriation to the country of origin.

• Rehabilitation in the host country.

• Resettlement in a third country (Refugee Watch Online, 2007).

ROLE OF UNITED NATIONS HIGH
COMMISSION FOR REFUGEES

More than 1,30,000 Bhutanese people of Nepali ethnicity have been compelled to live in exile for more than ten years. About 1,00,000 of them live at present in the UNHCR organized refugee camps in Morang and Jhapa districts of eastern Nepal. With the refugee crisis becoming more serious, some of the countries like United States, Canada, Australia, Denmark, Norway, New Zealand and The Netherlands have shown their sympathy and interest in resettling these refugees in their country. In 2006, US Secretary of State Population announced to resettle 60,000 Bhutanese refugees (Human Rights Watch, 2007).

After exhaustive efforts towards repatriation failed, several countries came together, with UNHCR and took initiatives for resettlement of refugees. In November 2007, the government of Nepal publicly accepted and supported for third country resettlement. Thereafter, the Nepal government, UNHCR and the International Organization for Migration and the resettlement countries began resettlement activities. To enjoy the activity and to enjoy the safety of the applicant, prevent threat and violence and anti-resettlement goods, the government established the armed police in the camps by the third country resettlement. UNHCR remains the first way to contact the refugees in order to be eligible for third country resettlement (UNHCR, 2018).

The world food programme works for food, ration and education for the refugees. They undertake the transportation of food in the camps. The Lutheran World Federation distributes the meals to the refugees, every two weeks and the association of medical doctors is responsible for medical services in the camps, CARITAS Australia is responsible for the education of refugee children, Bhutanese refugees serve as team teachers and the curriculum in accordance with the Nepalese public school system and request the livelihood of the repatriation the Bhutanese refugees remaining in Nepal. Although Bhutanese refugees considerably enjoy a bold attitude by the policy of opening camp, technically Bhutanese refugees are not eligible to work, earn property and run a business the situation has remained like this for the past two decades.

At present, many uplifts are found in the refugee camps. The elders and youths wants to return Bhutan to as grounds for hope. They want a quick solution. The elderly have begun to say, ‘If our bodies cannot be buried in our motherland, then everything is meaningless.’ They are fed up with living for long in troubled camps. They are deprived of citizenship and other political and human rights in Nepal. Moreover, they have bitter experiences and memories of displacement imposed upon them by the autocratic government of Bhutan. Therefore, refugees have a miserable life, are also becoming a real problem for Nepal as their presence in Nepal as a receiving country has led to economic, social, cultural and environmental crisis. The UNHCR and Nepal provided asylum to these refugees on a humanitarian ground.

Resettlement of the Bhutanese refugees in the third country is seen as the only solution, or an option for them as they are fed up with the long run camp lives with deplorable condition. For example, UNHCR staff member Tulsi Limbu was just a child when he saw the refugee arriving in Nepal. He adds:

I was astonished to see their challenging situation in terms of food and shelter. After spending 20 years in the refugee camps, resettlement is a great option in helping them to start their lives a fresh. I feel very proud that, somewhere, my small efforts were a part of this successful operation (UNHCR, 2013).

On December 1950, the United Nation High Commissioner for Refugees was established by the United Nations General Assembly (UNGA) and it began to officially function on 1 January 1951 with international agencies within the agenda of ‘protect and resolve refugee problem’ worldwide.

Between the late 1980s and mid-1990s, Bhutan saw the marginalization of its ethnic Nepalese population following protests in the early 1990s. As a result, more than 100,000 ethnic Nepalese fled Bhutan, with the vast majority settling in Nepal. By 1992 the government of Nepal and UNHCR the UN refugee agency had established seven refugee camps in eastern Nepal for the Bhutanese refugees. These camps are among the good refugee’s camps in the world, the government of Nepal and UNHCR deserve considerable credit for providing security, shelter, education and health care (UNHCR, 2008).

The Trend Report release, ‘UNHCR’ shows that at the beginning of 2010 the number of people forcibly displaced worldwide 43.3 million. This is the highest ducat on the mountain. The dramatic thing is not only these numbers are growing but the situation has become more protracted with never-ending conflicts and keeping the people as refugees since the last several decades. The utmost priority to be provided to these people remains shelter. As a brief organization in the field of human displacement UNHCR aims to enter even if these people have lost their home, they haven’t lost their future. At the beginning of 2012, more than 26 million people, 10.4 million refugees, 15.6 million IDPs were receiving protection or assistance including shelter from UNHCR.

The Bhutanese refugee’s issue being subjected and prioritized as minimal is one of the causes for the long-term non-resolution to the problem which is being done by the Bhutan and Nepal. The news of the 1990 mass demonstration in Bhutan was a surprise to the international community. All of a sudden, the international news media began reporting the physical assault, killings and arbitrary arrest of thousands of people. Henceforth, the Himalayan Kingdom of Bhutan came into focus worldwide.

In the beginning, the international community was not convinced about the true origin of the refugees. Bhutan had stressed that most of those in the camps were either illegal economic immigrants from Bhutan or poor Nepali people gathered from the surrounding areas for assistance by the international relief agencies. It is true in a sense, because one cannot differentiate between the local Nepalese with that of Bhutanese refugees due to similarities in food culture dress language and religion. For the international community, local assimilation would have been the perfect solution. After all, they all are ethnic Nepali people. But, if we see morally, Nepal is unable to afford Bhutanese refugees due to its social and economic problems. Therefore, the durable solution has become widely acceptable to the international community.

UNHCR and other agencies provide a range of services to support refugees in health, education, legal counselling, vocational skills and livelihoods.

MAIN OBJECTIVES

Some 60,000 of Bhutanese refugees in Nepal continuing with the UNHCR, although a number of refugees need protection and assistance. While UNHCR is planning to implement CBDP/TSI (Community Based Development Programme and Transitional Solution Initiatives) with the Government of Nepal and United Nation country team so that it can be implementing for the remaining population of around 34,000 in the host country (UNHCR, 2013).

Favourable Protection Environment

• Access to territory is improved and the risk of refoulement reduced.

• No credible cases of refoulement are reported.

Security from Violence and Exploitation

• The risk of sexual and gender-based violence (SGBV) is reduced and equality of the response to its improved.

• All survivors of SGBV receive support.

• The protection of children is strengthened.

Basic Needs and Essential Services

• The health status of the population is improved.

• All persons of concern have access to primary healthcare.

Durable Solutions

• The potential for resettlement is realized (UNHCR, 2013).

BASIC NEEDS AND ASSISTANCE

UNHCR is now the world leader in the provision of mass emergency shelter, distribution and delivery. Global coordination on international levels the emergency shelter conduct by UNHCR and IFRC at the country level. UNHCR led the emergency to shelter casting follow conflict, while lifesaving convenient throughout natural disasters.

They are trying to work with International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies and other partners as a cluster at the global level. To make sure that the global cluster response is more effective, predictable, and streamlined. In the emergency shelter response, UNHCR main partners are UN agencies government runners, private sectors, local NGOs, International NGOs, local community and the displaced community. The aim of UNHCR emergency shelters response it to reduce protection to prevent loss of life, in the following issues:

• Preparedness for emergency

• Leadership in emergency shelters

• Delivery

• Technical capacity

• Partnership

• Coordinance

• Shelter solution

UNHCR has capacity to respond to emergency needs of the affected population who were left nothing, UNHCR has capacity to building emergency and providing shelter to displaced persons, in word refugees and internally displaced persons. UNHCR has more than six decades of helping the world uprooted people.

CAPACITY BUILDING

As a core activity in strengthening ‘capacity building under the international protection no. 10: claims to refugees’ status within the context of Article 1A(2) of 1951 convention and the 1967 protocol relating to the situation of refugees of 3 December 2013, seeks to help in the protection of refugees though livelihood programmes by UNHCR, develop the capacity to strengthen and to make people self-sufficient in their places.

Capacity building activities are basically ensured under the law of protection for handling refugees’ issues, care and self-reliance but it cannot be generated without donor agencies, humanitarian assistance, civil society, NGOs and with the refugees itself.

Due to lack of income and means to earn a living, Bhutanese refugees are entirely dependent on relief agencies as they are not permitted by the host government to engage in any paid work or to produce goods for sale and work outside the camps. So, they work within confines of fields (Women’s Refugee Commission, 2006). Over time, they have developed alternative livelihood strategies, such as:

• They produce crops in the camps area and livestock activities.

• Receive incentives from aid agencies and remittance from family members abroad.

• Run a small-scale business in various sectors including small shops, drug stores, the sale of telephone cards, small restaurants and bars, transport of goods and persons, repair services (bicycles, cars and radios), hairdressing, money exchange, phone services, security and language tutoring or interpreting.

• Their production activities include carpentry and furniture making blacksmithing and welding, production of bricks and soap, baking and food processing and production of baskets, leatherwear, textiles and clothes.

• They work with humanitarian agencies or incentive work where formal employment is not allowed which provides a share of refugees with a regular income.

• They work in the position as teachers, nurses, community workers, office staff, cleaners, cooks and gardeners (Bruijn, 2009).

Sometimes refugees do adopt negative coping strategies when none of the alternatives provides structural relief or when households or individuals are faced with immediate crises. These strategies include selling off vital assets such as domestic items, clothes and blankets or part of the food rations, or reducing food intake and negotiating loans that cannot be repaid. Hence, they are forced to indulge in crime and illegal activities, such as fraud (e.g., receiving cash and material benefits for repatriation and then returning for re-registration) and theft (crops, cattle and other assets), or to selling sexual services and trafficking (Refugee Watch Online, 2007). Similarly, camps situated in areas are prone to violence and instability which are not favourable to establish productive and structural ways to earn a living. With the passage of time, the support system in the camps has come under increasing strains because of ‘donor fatigue’ which cuts in the provision of essential services, including food, fuel, medical care and shelter materials (Lænkholm, 2007). Again, the standard services extended to every refugee have now been limited to only most vulnerable ones.

Finally, it is evident that the level of development of the country of asylum is an essential factor in determining the well being and status of the refugees as the country’s capacity to assist refugees sets a standard for the living conditions.

Self-management skills are provided to vulnerable refugee women under the Bhutanese Refugee Women’s Forum operating in both the camps (UNHCR, 2000). It gives training for various sectors in business management; awareness-raising programmes on gender and domestic violence and leadership training, childcare centre, income generation for women and fire prevention are run for Refugees (UNHCR, 2000). Women held more than half of the decision-making positions in the camps, with two women serving as camp secretaries (UNHCR, 2007). Women’s groups are established in each of the camps and informal skills training, social awareness and functional literacy classes are provided to women with specific needs. Foundation of Bhutanese Refugee Aiding the Victims of Violence (BRAVVE) was founded to provide training to mentally challenged people, many of whom were tortured in jail, traumatized and disabled. People are provided training in tailoring, weaving, embroidery, shoemaking, typing and computer literacy (WHO, 1999). Practising these skills enabled the mentally challenged individuals to be productive. Establishment of a credit scheme helped them purchase sewing machines, equipment and set up small businesses. Both UNHCR and WFP provide funding to Caritas for Vocational Training (VT) to youth from refugee communities who have dropped out of high school. WFP supports for the training of medical staff, implemented by the AMDA. Some 40 women of an equal number of women from the refugee population and adjacent host communities participated in an eighteen-month course in midwifery and nursing (UNHCR/WFP, 2012). WFP with LWF and UNHCR as implementing partners supports a home gardening project to supplement the basic needs.

SOLUTIONS

According to the refugee-budget of UNHCR for Bhutanese Refugees has been increasing almost annually since the year 2000 such as 2000-USD 5.1 million; 2001-5.3 million; 2002-5.6 million; 2003-5.5 million; 2004-6.9 million; 2005-6.8 million. 2007, 2008 (UNHCR, 2000), instead, believing that return provided the only humane solution to refugee problems, the UNHCR essentially ran long-term programmes in an emergency mode which were damaging to the long-term welfare of refugees stuck in protracted camp situations. They have already spent years in remote and forgotten camps and lack in wage-earning opportunities, self-sufficiency. So, it needs a solution where they can become productive and contribute to their host societies until the refugees are willing or can return home.

Refugees usually return when they consider it is safe to do so when other interests are met. Moreover, the UNHCR is not in the best position to determine when it is best or most appropriate for repatriation. It has remained only as an organization in a more general humanitarian emergency. So, it has compromised its capacity and willingness to provide protection and has put the agency at the mercy of a much broader set of political and strategic calculations. Because UNHCR needs to raise more and more voluntary funds for its operations, obtain access to increasingly volatile internal situations, win the confidence of competing actors and promote compromise solutions, the agency is not well placed to stand up for protection principles regarding refugees (Loescher, 2001). The office also lacks a strong self-identity and remains uncertain about the precise role it should fulfill with the broader framework of international relations.

DURABLE SOLUTIONS PROMOTED
BY UNHCR

The UNHCR has outlined three options to residents of a refugee camp of protracted refugee situation (PRS). These are:

• Voluntary return (repatriation) to their home country.

• Local integration in the country of first asylum.

• Resettlement in a third country.

REPATRIATION

Voluntary return or repatriation to their home country in conditions of safety and dignity is the most desirable outcome for the individual, their society and the international community. Most refugees want to return to their homes when it is safe to do so. Support for reconstruction, re-integrating and reconciliation helps ensure the success of repatriation as a durable solution. Regarding the local integration of Bhutanese refugees, though it may appear as a solution to the problem, it will legitimize the state of Bhutan to denationalise its population, in the long run ‘it could encourage more displacements’ (Chetri, 1997). Refugees insist they won’t go back to Bhutan. But they want to back to their land and houses and with some assurance of safety. They would like the office of the UNHCR together with that of the UNHCR to be involved. ‘We’re not asking for the sky,’ says Ratan Gazmere of the Association of Human Rights Activists, based in Nepal. These conditions are unlikely to be met, however. As Bhutanese refugees were forced to leave their homes, land and properties in Bhutan large numbers of houses and land left by the refugees in southern Bhutan have been confiscated by the government and have been used to relocate people from other parts of Bhutan or for government purposes (COHRE, 2008). So, it would be difficult to relocate them in the kingdom of Bhutan.

However, in August 2005 the United Nations Principles on Housing and property restitution for refugees and displaced persons were adopted, ‘Pinheiro principles’ (COHRE, 2008). These principals provide clear guidelines to make it possible for the Bhutanese refugees to return home. Such possibility applies to all refugees irrespective of which option repatriation, local integrating or third country resettlement, the Bhutanese refugees choose. Most importantly, making repatriation possible, the Bhutanese governments should recognize that the Bhutanese refugees have a right to return. All refugees have the right to go back voluntarily to their former homes, lands or places where they used to live, in safety and dignity. That mean that persons displaced against their will must be allowed to return to their former homes and lands, if and whenever they wish to do so.

LOCAL INTEGRATION

Local integration in the country of first asylum is the second option suggested by UNHCR when voluntary repatriation is not possible. It is so because the country of first asylum is usually in the same region to refugee’s home country and cultural ties can make the integration process more accessible. In the case of Bhutanese refugees, their first logically, the country for asylum is India, but they have their camps and livelihood in Nepal. Local integration is the process in which refuges settle permanently in the host country (Jacobsen, 2001). However, due to political reasons, regional integration in Nepal has not the preferred solution.

The first obstacle is that Bhutanese refugees are perceived as a temporary inconvenience to the host country because they rely heavily on government and international assistance. It creates the sentiment that if locally integrated refugees are not able to sustain themselves without outside assistance that was available in the camps, they will consequently become a permanent burden to the host country.

Second, refugees lack of belonging to the host country due to discrimination. These are great obstacles in the way of local integrations, who often prefer to return to their home country as soon as they deem it safe or live in the hope of being resettled in a third country.

Third, for local integration to take place, it is fundamental to have the participation and willingness of the host government. Preliminary conditions that need to exist before local integration can take place include the involvement and cooperation of the host government.

RESETTLEMENT IN A ‘THIRD COUNTRY’

Resettlement in a third country is used to protect refugees whose life, liberty, safety, health or fundamental human rights are at risk in their country of asylum. It is promoted by UNHCR where returning to their home country, or local integration may not be suitable or as part of a responsibility sharing arrangement. Due to protracted situations resettlement has become a key element in the system of refugee protection. In TCR, refugees are transferred from the country in which they found refuge to another country which agrees to welcome them. The UNHCR generally gives priority to individuals with a high protection need, as well as women and highly vulnerable families. This kind of resettlement is usually recommended for populations that are victims of protracted situations and when neither repatriation nor local integration seems possible.

The effective implantation to a third country presents numerous challenges. First, it depends on refugees to integrate into the new country. They must be able to adapt themselves to the life, culture and socio-economic structures in the host country. It implies that refugees need to take on a wage-earning activity having a minimum level of education that is necessary. But in Bhutanese refugees’ situation, they have a language barrier to integrate.

PROTECTION

These are violence that are directed against a person on the basis of their gender or sex. It includes acts that inflict physical, mental, or sexual harm or suffering, threats of such acts, coercion and other deprivations of liberty. Examples of gender-based violence are sexual violence, domestic violence, emotional and psychological abuse, trafficking, forced prostitution, sexual exploitation, sexual harassment and harmful traditional practices, e.g. Female genital mutilation, or widow cleansing. The women’s commission for women and children defines the term ‘gender-based violence’ as, physical, sexual, psychological and economic or socio-cultural attacks by strangers, by family members, by armies and police forces, even by peacekeepers. It includes harassments, sexual exploitation and trafficking (UNHCR, 2001). Though GBV can occur to anyone, i.e. male or female, young or old it disproportionately affects women and girls.

Similarly GBV is unique to refugee situations. Human rights watch examines the uneven response of UNHCR and the government of Nepal to GBV in refugee camps in Nepal despite reforms by UNHCR though one can experience some positive aspects in the camps but cannot be confirmed. Due to unemployment people are not able to carry their socio-economic roles and increase of family tensions. This results in the subsequent rise in the use of alcohol by men within the refugees’ community and leads to aggressive behaviour towards women and results in SGBV.

It has been argued that gender relations in refugees camp are influenced by traditional ideologies and are shaped by memories of home as a domestic sphere of the patriarchal family. And it is well known that the Bhutanese refugees’ culture is a patriarchal dominant. So, within the camps, there is a tradition where women bound to remain within the periphery of household activities and dependent on men in the process of getting aid. They have a lower and subordinate position and are subjected to various forms of violence and discrimination. In the case of women the main causes of being the victim are the economic hardship and lack of education and skills. Many women are forced to cross the border to seek better and secure lives are involved in sex businesses workplace harassment and abuse, vulnerability, personal safety and security question of sustainability of income and assistance have become a daily challenge to human right watch reports, SGBV is widespread and have been occurring among Bhutanese refugees in many forms including domestic violence, e.g. fighting and sexual assault, harassment, trafficking, enforced prostitution and sexual violence. Also in the camps, cases of polygamy and child marriage against refugee women, including refugee girls, were reported. Perpetrators of this violence against women include not only partners but also humanitarian aid workers, sexual harassment com-mitted by Nepalese government officers, most of the teachers, working for NGOs implementing partners. In 2001, an investigation team from the inspector general’s office investigated all camps with a particular focus on the incidents of SGBV against female refugees, including children. The team reported a total of 47 cases in which ten refugee teachers; one refugee health worker, one sanitation volunteer and two Nepali government officials were said to have been addressed (UNHCR, 2001).

According to WCRWC, incidents of gender-based violence in camps include an attack on women and girls collecting firewood located near to forests (UNHCR, 2006). These are again the results due to a shortage in kerosene supply and which have necessitated firewood collection mainly by those refugees without having sufficient means (UNHCR, 2006). Despite all limitations and discrimination, some definite improvement and steps towards empowerment are seen. Women hence are managing to have a good education and raising their awareness. In recent years, they have found along with colleague ‘Voice for change’, only independent women’s organization in the camps which advocates for women’s rights. It has given women the opportunity to express themselves and defend themselves against violence. It has also helped to raise women’s voices and has created a platform for discussion, for sharing experiences and finding solutions. Its primary objective is to highlight the issues, inform women and help them understand their problems. Their advocacy activities have been sustained by local NGOs such as TEW Nepal, by the Global Fund for Women and INGO. Hence it can be said that the external influences of international aid workers have made changes through programmes which include training, information support services and for local women and public education events. Gender-based violence cases have been given the priority in the third country resettlement.

The OHCHR plays a role in monitoring and investigating human rights abuses, including those directed against women and girls. UNICEF, for its part, responds to the specific needs of refugee. NGOs are also crucial protection sectors. They partner with UN agencies and work on their own to implement programmes to prevent and respond to SGBV in refugee settings.

HEALTH AND SANITATION

The refugee experiences have significant impact on health due to several adverse situations in their country of origin and during their flight and still in the life in exile. The following are some of the deprivation, civil unrest separation and loss of family and friends, imprisonment, threat, beatings, torture and rape, overcrowded, poor hygiene and undernutrition, inadequate health care due to the distraction of infrastructure, disruption in preventive services and limited health services while fleeing or in exile (Mitchell, 2003). Some of the common health problems seen among Bhutanese refugees are: Psychological; issues including PTSD, anxiety or depression; due to torture, poor health as a result of poor nutrition, diet, lack of fluoridated water, infectious diseases including ongoing risks from tuberculosis and chronic intestinal parasites, underimmunization, under-managed chronic condition such as hypertension, diabetes and chronic pain and lastly, delayed growth and development in children including deficits in hearing and speech (Mitchell, 2003).

In 2010, due to all allegation of the disproportionately high number of suicides among refugees resettled in the US, in January 2011, the IOM in coordination with UNHCR conducted a three-week assessment on psychosocial well-being and suicide risk factors among refugees in Nepal and the ones resettled in the US. Results for this confirm that the number of suicides among refugees in Nepal camp is disproportionately high and the rate among refugees resettled in the US is even higher (Schininà, Sharma, Gorbacheva & Mishra, 2011). Besides, health programmes and awareness are provided under UNHCR among refugee camps mainly on subjects related to health education, including HIV/AIDS prevention, family planning, inoculations, mother and child health projects, ambulance services and maintenance of health facilities (UNHCR, 2008) although, different health and nutrition programme are implemented in the camps. In 2007, the Women’s Refugee Commission launched a major research project to assess the situation for those living with disabilities among displaced and conflict-affected populations. Because people living with disabilities may be left behind during flight, or may not survive the journey, they are often not identified or counted in registration or data collection exercises; they are excluded from or unable to access mainstream assistance programmes and forgotten when specialized services are set up.

The WRC was particularly concerned about discrimination by their gender, age and social status, as well as their disability. Some positive examples of the refugee community outreach health programmes for persons with a disability were found in the refugee camps (Reilly, 2007). Regarding the availability of inclusive education for children with disability in refugee camps in Nepal, there was successful early childhood intervention programmes to identify children with disability and help them integrate into mainstream schools (Reilly, 2007).

Health status of refugee is a complex issue as it is related to numerous factors, such as food supply, water and sanitation, shelter, education, environmental factors, health services, etc. So to understand the issue, one needs to have a comprehensive approach. Primarily, refugee camps are too compact and overcrowded, which may result in easy spread or transmission of infectious disease. The provision of adequate sanitation services is crucial to prevent communicable diseases and epidemics while ensuring good health and dignity. This part of the study includes human excreta disposal, waste water disposal, solid wasted and clinical waste management and hygiene promotion as a part of sanitation. The collection and disposal of waste should not endanger the individuals and the community. In Nepal, sanitation facilities are designed with women’s needs in mind and to avoid vulnerability to SGBV. All families have designated restroom that is shared with one other family and this has provided adequate sanitation coverage. On critically reviewing the sanitation situation in the refugee camps, camps are adequately planned with adequate infrastructure with the refugee managing most of the relief activities with agency coordination. Solid waste management and vector control were carried out through the construction and repair of latrines spraying in the camps. Camps sanitary conditions remained good; vector-borne diseases were kept at negligible levels (UNHCR, 2004). Restrooms were maintained, garbage was collected and clean-up and campaigns conducted regularly within the camps. Construction materials were provided to refugee families to replace over 2,400 latrine roofs and sanitation volunteers helped refugee families to shift close to 3,400 latrine pits. In 2004, a joint solid waste collection, transportation and disposal project was implemented for refugees and host community residents in Beldangi and Sanischari camps (UNHCR, 2004). Shapkota Prajapati describing the Water Supply and Sanitation of Refugee Camp in Nepal writes, ‘Excreta disposal, solid waste management and wastewater disposal have been found satisfactory and people’s participation is an example to be followed elsewhere’ (Kota & Lee, 2006). UNHCR/ WFP Joint Assessment Mission Report founded that in general the activities related to water supply and sanitation were functioning well. Periodic clean-up campaigns are organized and garbage is disposed at proper site safe for both the refugee and local population (UNHCR, 2008).

FOOD AND NUTRITION STATUS AMONG REFUGEES

In the refugee camp situation like in Nepal, people are entirely dependent on humanitarian assistance and food aid. This is primarily because of the host country’s policies which restrict income-generation and agricultural activities of refugees. Hence, they entirely depend in the WFP assistance for food which ensures access to adequate quality of food to support life and preserve dignity of refugees. It has the responsibility for the management of the entire food delivery and distribution whereas UNHCR supplements the rations of people with specific needs such as dried skimmed milk was provided to malnourished refugee children. Safe drinking and domestic water supply are provided in all camps.

TABLE 7.2: FOOD AND NUTRITION STATUS
AMONG REFUGEES

Camp | Population | General Ration Beneficiaries
Beldangi
Sanischari | 37,311
11,279 | 36,679
10,993
TOTAL | 48,590 | 47,672

Source: UNHCR/WFP Joint Assessment Mission Report (2008-2012) (UNHCR/WFP, 2012).

Food rations are distributed every two weeks to each household in proportion to the number of members in the family. Refugees receive ‘food baskets’ containing rice, lentils, vegetable oil, sugar, salt, wheat soya blend and some vegetables. In addition, the food ration reflects cultural and dietary preference of refugees (UNHCR/ WFP, 2012). UNHCR maintains a standard of below 2,100 kilo-calories for food and nutrition as average number of kilocalories per person per day.

TABLE 7.3: FOOD AND NUTRITION STATUS
AMONG REFUGEES

Commodity | General rations (grams/persons/day)
Rice (polished white) | 400
Pulses (yellow split peas) | 60
Vegetable Oil/Palmolian Oil (Vitamin A fortified) | 25
Super cereals (Wheat soya Blend with Sugar) | 35
Sugar | 20
Salt | 7.5

Source: UNHCR/WFP Joint Assessment Mission Report (2008-12) (UNHCR/ WFP, 2012).

UNHCR recommended that each refugee receive more than 2,100 calories per day, but often camps fall short of this standard. Even if a refugee receives the recommended number of calories per day, caloric intake is further reduced as refugees tend to sell food rations for other non-food goods. Moreover, it is not only the quality of food that is insufficient, but lack of food variety, fruits and vegetables also causes many refugees to suffer from deficiencies in essential vitamins and minerals leading to variety of diseases. However, a market in the camps and gardening provides refugee families with fresh vegetables, condiments and other items to supplement their diets. But the lack of farmland restricts families from growing more vegetables. To minimize this deficiency among refugee children, all adolescent girls received iron tablets and all children attending school received deworming tablets (UNHCR/ WFP, 2012). Hence over the year the provision of vegetable provided has been reduced, it forced people to earn income and buy food to supplement their ration and to ensure that their diet remains healthy. Similarly, a nutrition and food security strategic plan has been developed in coordination with operational partners to provide improved the nutrition situation among refugees in Nepal (UNHCR/WFP, 2012).

WFP, UNHCR, the RCU and LWF participate in the committee and together agree who would be added or removed from distribution and registration lists in the camp. The committee review the list of departure to third country and adjust the food distribution lists accordingly whereas Asian Medical Doctor’s Association (AMDA) is responsible for post distribution food basket monitoring (UNHCR/WFP, 2012). Lastly, as noted above, all the overall food and nutritional status of the refugees is satisfactory.

UNHCR is responsible through its partners for the distribution of non-food items. To prevent environmental degradation particularly from the forest and mainly the increasing fuel prices the regular supply of kerosene to the camps ceased in December 2005. It was used as the most viable source of fuel for cooking in the camps since 1992. Kerosene, replaced by briquettes has hugely impacted on the refugees as briquettes burn slowly, produces a foul smoke and cannot be used as lighting fuel. It prevents children from studying after dark.

REFUGEE WELFARE

Nepal is not signatory in the 1951 refugee convention or the 1967 protocol. Refugees are considered foreigners and are not allowed to engage in economic activities or own any kind of property (UNHCR/WFP, 2012).

Since 2008, the most significant change in refugee welfare has been seen in remittance from abroad. Many shops advertising money transfers are located outside of the camp. Although, these services are utilized by beneficiaries of both the communities. For increment of their diet they use to purchase food and non-food items. They are also used to pay off debts, to provide loans to others, or set aside for contingencies such as fire (UNHCR/WFP, 2012).

Some refugees have started business or open shop in the camp. Other have used the fund to pursue their skill training or advance education. The standard of living has increased in the camp population; it is clearly visible to mission members in the electricity supply, TV sets and satellite dish antenna (UNHCR/WFP, 2012).

SKILL AND VOCATIONAL TRAINING

Skill trainings are very useful for the refugees so that they can be considered for the resettlement. Here the list of skills includes computer software and hardware, finance, driving, tailoring, housekeeping, hair dressing, beautification, masonry, carpentry, plumbing, electric wiring and repair of radios/electric equipment (UNHCR/WFP, 2012). Although, some refugees have complained that in many courses they were not eligible for selected courses as they did not qualify the eligibility criteria (UNHCR/WFP, 2012).

With the support of WFP, the Bhutanese Refugee Women’s Forum (BRWF) implements a Loan Scheme. Single women, large families, families without extra support are the beneficiaries. Apart from that at the large scale most of the refugees hesitate to take advantage of the scheme (UNHCR/WFP, 2012).

UNHCR has invested in extension in capacity building, Health workers by means of training, orientation and regular monitoring and supervision by the staff, but as per resettlement health workers poses a serious challenge to the goal of maintaining the quality of health services to the camp population (UNHCR/WFP, 2012).

FUNDING

UNHCR presented a global needs-based budget of US$ 3,924 million for 2013, for approval to its executive committee for requirement in October 2012. In emergency needs the fund reaches a precedent level of US$ 5,335 million in total requirement by the end of December 2013. However, the funds available could cover only 60 per cent, leaving many of the needs of people a concern to UNHCR (UNHCR, 2012). It should be noted that in this report all expenditure has been modified cash basis, where (UNHCR, 2012) as UNHCR’s financial statements are prepared in accordance with International Public Sector Accounting Standards (IPSAS).

UNHCR’s financial requirement in Nepal has been increasing with the reduction of refugee population in the camps, with the aim of improving refugee’s living standard. In comparison of 2012 Nepal’s overall budget requirement slightly decreased. While hosting refugee community will prioritize the resettlement programme with UNHCR (UNHCR, 2013).

Other urban community will continue, undertaking advocacy to ensure the new constitution provision with regards to citizen provision. Short falls consequences in Fund:

• It will hurt the opportunity of skills and resettlement of the refugees.

• Refugees will suffer in reduction of education in schools, vocational trainings and lack of resources for replacement.

• They drastically suffer in basic services and non-food items with supply of fuel and constructions of semi-permanent camps for vulnerable.

• Issues like SGBV would be negatively affected (UNHCR, 2013).

Comparative Planning Figures for Nepal by UNHCR, 2007 and December 2013.

CONCLUSION

The efforts of the UNHCR for well being of the Bhutanese refugees in Nepal, who moved from Bhutan in 1990, have been tremendous, meanwhile they have been constrained by the situation rising on ground. Having been thrown away from their homes and motherland, livelihood and for individual development of the refugees, are critically disrupted and they have been largely dependent on humanitarians’ assistance and policies and local conditions in the host country. It is commendable that the UNHCR through its programmes namely basic needs and assistance, capacity building, has attempted to provide durable solutions like repatriation and their local integration. These solutions have eased the settlement, but refugees still face the tough times in fulfilling their wish to go back to Bhutan and settle on their erstwhile homeland, especially the land where their ancestors had settled centuries ago which they are denied now. It is notable that a third country resettlement of the refugees around the globe requires protection, health and sanitation, food and nutrition and other welfare programmes and in the case of the Bhutanese refuges, efforts of the UNHCR and other NGOs and International NGOs can neither be denied nor be ignored. Among the many of the UNHCR led programmes, the most effective contribution has been the financial assistance provided by the UNHCR. In Nepal, to facilitate refugees’ integration into the local context and to avoid resentment among the locals surrounding refugee camps, residents for certain assistance are targeted, such as, for example in health care, education, water and food supply. Community-based projects in the camps has been often more efficient in providing services. Implementing partners are working in closer cooperation with the refugees themselves. Without adequate and timely protection mechanisms and proper community-support, the protection and assistance to these vulnerable sections would be more critical.

TABLE 7.4: COMPARATIVE PLANNING FIGURES FOR NEPAL
BY UNHCR, 2007 AND DECEMBER 2013

Type of Populaton | Origin | Total | Of whom assist by UNHCR | % of female | % of under 18
Refugees | Bhutan | 107,800 | 107,800 | 49 | 34
| Tibetans | 20,200 | – | 48 | –
| Various | 220 | 220 | - | –
Refugee-like situations | Bhutan | 2,500 | – | 49 | 34
Asylum seekers | Bhutan | 1,600 | – | 42 | 31
| Various | 80 | 80 | – | –
IDPs | | 50,000 | 50,000 | – | –
Returnees (IDPs) | | 50,000 | 50,000 | – | –
Stateless | | 800,000 | – | – | –
Other of concern | Various | 140 | 130 | – | –
TOTAL | | 1,032,540 | 208,230 | |

Source: UNHCR Global Report 2007 (UNHCR, 2007).

TABLE 7.5: PERSONS OF CONCERN 2018

Type of | Origin | January 2018 | December 2018
Populaton | | Total in country | Of whom assisted by UNHCR | Total in country | Of whom assisted by UNHCR
Refugees | Bhutan | 32,338 | 39,810 | 28,190 | 28,190
| Tibetans | 15,000 | – | 15,000 | –
| Various | 280 | 280 | 280 | 280
Persons in Refugee-like situations | Bhutan | 1,890 | – | 1,890 | –
Asylum seekers | Various | 20 | 20 | 30 | 30
IDPs | Nepal | 50,000 | – | 50,000 | –
Stateless people | Stateless | * | * | * | *
Other of concern | | 660 | 250 | 660 | 250
TOTAL | | 100,188 | 40,360 | 96,050 | 28,750

Source: UNHCR Global Appeal Report Update 2018.

Also, it is not the issue of the third country settlement and improving the life quality, the other aspect of the Bhutanese refugees in past three decades has revolved around the question of the life with dignity and access to civil, political, economic and educational rights that have been guaranteed under the universal declaration of the human rights, convention on civil and political rights, followed by the convention of the economic rights. While the refugees hold no political rights, allowing them to participate in the process of the governance, they are left to rely on the goodwill and efforts of the agencies like local NGOs and the international agencies like UNHCR. Further, since the ousting of the Nepali-speaking Bhutanese refugees to a third country, their situation has remained static rather turning into complete change. Also, a third country settlement of the refugees does not guarantee the change into their lives, it only guarantees shelter and food with other limited options for education and skill development. With efforts made at the non-governmental level, Nepal has hosted them for three decades now, but the local resistance in the host country is wide open. The Maoist insurgency in the past decade and unstable political turf in Nepal, options for the refugees in terms of political will to pressurize the government of Bhutan to accept them and even improve their life quality in Nepal remains a challenge. Hence, the political will and government response of the host country is the need of the hour for the wellness and hopes for the repatriation of the refugees in Bhutan in near future.

REFERENCES

Amnesty International (December 1992). Bhutan: Human Rights Violations Against the Nepali-Speaking Population in the South. Retrieved 26 March 2018 from Amnesty International https://www.amnesty.org/download/Documents/192000/asa140041992en.pdf

Amenesty International (December 1994). Bhutan: Forced Exile. Retrieved 25 November 2018, from Amenesty International: https://www.amnesty.org/download/Documents/184000/asa140041994en.pdf

Bhutan Population (18 December 2018). Retrieved from Worldometers: http://www.worldometers.info/world-population/bhutan-population/

Bruijn, B.D. (July 2009). Human Development Research Paper 2009/25, The Living Conditions and Well-being of Refugees. Retrieved 11 June 2018 from UNDP: http://hdr.undp.org/sites/default/files/hdrp_2009_25.pdf

Chetri, R. (1997). Bhutanese Lhotshampas: Victims of Ethinic Cleansing. In T. K. Bose and R. Manchanda, State, Citizens and Outsiders: The Uprooted People of South Asia (p. 265). Kathmandu: South Asia Forum.

COHRE (March 2008). Hoping to Return Home Housing, Land and Property Restitution Rights for Bhutanese Refugees and Displaced Persons. Retrieved 12 November 2018 from Centre on Housing Rights and Evictions (COHRE): http://www.chs.ubc.ca/archives/files/Hoping%20to%20Return%20Home%20Housing,%20land%20and%20property%20restitution%20rights%20for%20Bhutanese%20Refuges%20and%20displaced%20persons.pdf

Frelick, B. (30 March 2011). For Bhutan’s Refugees, There’s No Place Like Home. Retrieved 25 December 2015, from Human Rights Watch: https://www.hrw.org/news/2011/03/30/bhutans-refugees-theres-no-place-home

Human Rights Watch (May 2007). Last Hope: The Need for Durable Solutions for Bhutanese Refugees in Nepal and India. London: MacMillan Press with UNRISD. Retrieved from Human Rights Watch.

Hutt, M. (2003). Unbecoming Citizens: Culture, Nationhood and the Fight of Refugess from Bhutan.New Delhi: Oxford University Press.

——(2005). The Bhutanese Refugees: Between Verification, Repatriation and Royal Realpolitic. Peace and Democracy in South Asia, 45.

Jacobsen, K. (2001). The Forgotten Solution: Local Integration for Refugees in Developing Countries 96 Packard Avenue Medford, 02155. Working Paper, Center Tufts University, Fletcher School of Law & Diplomacy and Feinstein International Famine, Massachusetts . Retrieved 23 March 2018, from https://www.unhcr.org/research/working/3b7d24059/forgotten-solution-local-integration-refugees-developing-countries-karen.html

Kharat, R. (2007). Indo-Bhutan Relations: Strategic Perspective. In K. Warikoo, Himalayan Frontier of India (pp. 155-6). New York: Routledge.

Kota, P. and Lee, S.-H. (October-December 2006). Water Supply and Sanitation: A Case Study of Timai Bhutanese Refugee Camp in Nepal.Thammasat lnt, 2(4), 65-7.

Lænkholm, C. (2 December 2007). Resettlement for Bhutanese Refugees. Forced Migration Review (29).

Loescher, G. (Spring 2001). The UNHCR and World Politics: State Interests vs. Institutional Autonomy. The International Migration Review, 35(01), pp. 36-56.

MHA, GoB (1958). The Nationality Law of Bhutan, 1958. Retrieved 11 December 2018, from National Council of Bhutan: http://www.nationalcouncil.bt/assets/uploads/docs/acts/2017/Nationality-law-of-Bhutan-1958_Eng.pdf

Mitchell, S. (2003). Health Care for Refugees. Asia Pacific Family Medicine. Retrieved 13 November 2018 from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/epdf/10.1046/j.1444-1683.2003.00063.x

Refugee Watch Online (22 May 2007). Bhutanese Refugees: Pawn in the Hands of Governments and Politicians? Retrieved 25 October 2018, from Refugee Watch online: http://refugeewatchonline.blogspot.com/2007/05/bhutanese-refugees-pawn-in-hands-of.html

Reilly, R. (2007). Disabilities among refugees and conflict-affected populations. Forced Migration Review(35), pp. 8-10.

Rose, E.L. (1977). The Politics of Bhutan. Ithaka: Cornell University.

Schininà, G., Sharma, S., Gorbacheva, O., & Mishra, A. (2011). Who am I?: Assessment of psychosocial needs and suicide risk factors among Bhutanese refugees in Nepal and after the third country resettlement. Geneva: Migration Health Research Portall. Retrieved 20 May 2017, from https://migrationhealthresearch.iom.int/who-am-i-assessment-psychosocial-needs-and-suicide-risk-factors-among-bhutanese-refugees-nepal-and

UNHCR (2000). Nepal: Mid-Year Report 2000. Retrieved from UNHCR: https://www.unhcr.org/afr/3e6f1b770.pdf

——(1 January 2000). The State of The World’s Refugees 2000: Fifty Years of Humanitarian Action. Retrieved 23 March 2016, from UNHCR: https://www.unhcr.org/publications/sowr/4a4c754a9/state-worlds-refugees-2000-fifty-years-humanitarian-action.html

——(2001). Global Report. Retrieved 1 April 2018, from UNHCR: https://www.unhcr.org/research/working/3b7d24059/forgotten-solution-local-integration-refugees-developing-countries-karen.html

——(2004). Global Report: Nepal. UNHCR. Retrieved 11 December 2017, from https://www.unhcr.org/publications/fundraising/42ad4da50/unhcr-global-report-2004-nepal.html

——(2006). Women’s Commission For Refugee Women and Children. Retrieved 19 April 2018, from Library of Congress: https://www.loc.gov/item/lcwa00089057/

—— (2007). Global Report. Retrieved 12 November 2018, from unhcr: https://www.unhcr.org/gr07/

——(2008). Global Report: Partnerships. Retrieved 19 May 2018, from UNHCR: https://www.unhcr.org/4a2d1a012.pdf

—— (2010). Global Trends 2010. Retrieved 25 December 2017, from UNHCR: https://www.unhcr.org/statistics/country/4dfa11499/unhcr-global-trends-2010.html

——(2012). Displacement: The New 21st Century Challenge/Global Trends 2012. Retrieved 11 May 2018, from UNHCR: https://www.unhcr.org/statistics/country/51bacb0f9/unhcr-global-trends-2012.html

——(2013). Global Appeal Update. UNHCR. Retrieved 11 December 2018, from https://www.unhcr.org/ga13/index.xml

——(2013). Global Report. Retrieved 12 January 2016, from UNHCR: https://www.unhcr.org/gr13/index.xml

—— (1 May 2013). Refugee resettlement referral from Nepal reaches six-figure mark. Retrieved 23 November 2018, from UNHCR: https://www.unrefugees.org/news/refugee-resettlement-referral-from-nepal-reaches-six-figure-mark/

——(2018). Resettlement. Retrieved 19 December 2018, from UNHCR: https://www.unhcr.org/resettlement.html

UNHCR/WFP (2012). Joint Assessment Mission Report Assistance to the Refugees from Bhutan in Nepal (18 June–8 July 2012). Retrieved 26 June 2018, from World Food Programme: https://documents.wfp.org/stellent/groups/public/documents/ena/wfp193224.pdf?iframe

WHO (1999). Making a Difference. Retrieved 13 July 2018, from World Health Organisation: https://www.who.int/whr/1999/en/whr99_en.pdf?ua=1

Women’s Refugee Commission (2006). Beyond Firewood: Fuel Alternatives and Protection Strategies for Displaced Women and Girls. WRC. Retrieved 30 October 2016, from https://www.womensrefugeecommission.org/firewood/resources/165-beyond-firewood-fuel-alternatives-and-protection-strategies-for-displaced-women-and-girls